Now when Jesus was born in Bethlehem of
Judaea in the days of Herod the king,
behold, wise men from the east
came to Jerusalem saying,
"Where is he who is born king of the
Jews?
For we saw his star in the east and have
come to worship him."
When Herod the king heard it, he was
troubled and all Jerusalem with him.
Gathering together all the chief priests
and scribes of the people, he
asked them where the Christ would be
born.
They said to him, "In Bethlehem of
Judaea,
for thus it is written through the
prophet,
'You Bethlehem, land of Judah,
are in no way least among the princes of
Judah,
for out of you shall come forth a
governor who shall shepherd my people
Israel.'"
Then Herod secretly called the wise men
and learned from them exactly what time
the star appeared.
He sent them to Bethlehem and said,
"Go and search diligently for the young
child.
When you have found him, bring me word
so that I also may come and worship
him."
They, having heard the king, went their
way. And behold, the star which they saw
in the east went before them until it
came and stood over where the young
child was.
When they saw the star, they rejoiced
with exceedingly great joy.
They came into the house and saw the
young child with Mary his
mother, and they fell down and worshiped
him.
Opening their treasures, they offered to
him gifts, gold, frankincense,
and myrrh.
Being warned in a dream that they
shouldn't return to Herod, they went
back to their own country another way.
Now when they had departed, behold, an
angel of the Lord appeared to Joseph in
a dream saying,
"Arise and take the young child and his
mother and flee into Egypt and stay
there until I tell you.
For Herod will seek the young child
to destroy him."
He arose and took the young child and
his mother by night, and departed into
Egypt, and was there until the death of
Herod, that it might be fulfilled which
was spoken by the Lord through the
prophet saying,
"Out of Egypt I called my son."
Then Herod, when he saw that he was
mocked by the wise men,
was exceedingly angry, and sent
out and killed all the male children who
were in Bethlehem and in all the
surrounding countryside  from 2
years old and under,
according to the exact time which he had
learned from the wise men.
Then that which  was spoken by
Jeremiah the prophet was fulfilled
saying,
"A voice was heard in Rama,
lamentation, weeping, and great
mourning,
Rachel weeping for her children.
She wouldn't be comforted because they
are no more."
But when Herod was dead, behold, an
angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to
Joseph in Egypt saying,
"Arise and take the young child and his
mother, and go into the land of Israel,
for those who sought the young child's
life are dead."
He arose and took the young child and
his mother, and came into the land of
Israel.
But when he heard that Archelaus was
reigning over Judea in the place of his
father Herod, he was afraid to go there.
Being warned in a dream, he withdrew
into the region of Galilee, and came and
lived in a city called Nazareth, that it
might be fulfilled which was spoken
through the prophets, "He will be called
a Nazarene."